Hello, I'm your host David Bernard and
my guest today is Dan Lfield. After
helping Code Academy scale ARR from 10
million to 55 million and working as a
product manager on Uber Eats, Dan now
consults with startups looking to
increase subscription revenue and blogs
about his learnings at
subscriptionindex.com. On the podcast, I
talk with Dan about estimating the ROI
of product changes before building them.
Calculating your subscription apps
growth ceiling and why you shouldn't
make assumptions about what is and isn't
working in other apps. Hey Dan, thanks
so much for joining me on the podcast
today. Yeah. Hey, what's up David?
Thanks for having me. So, you've been
blogging up a storm the last couple of
years. I've linked to your posts a ton
in the Subub newsletter. I've tweeted
out links to your blogs, posted about
them on LinkedIn, and commented on
LinkedIn. So, I wanted to have you on to
talk more in depth about some of these
things that you've been writing about.
Of course, you've had a ton of great
experience at Code Academy and worked
with consulting clients who you've
helped with monetization. And so, I want
to dig into some of these writings that
you've done the past couple of years.
And one of the more interesting topics
that you've kind of touched on here and
there is this idea of focusing on the
ROI of projects. This is a really tough
one. So first of all like just tell me
what what you mean by that like high
level overview and then we can kind of
dig into the specifics of how you
actually determine the ROI of a project.
Yeah, sure. I'd say it's the thing you
kind of learn the hard way as a product
manager. You know, I was at Code Academy
for 5 years. I saw us grow from about 10
million AR R to about 55 million ARR.
You know, obviously there's a ton of
factors in that, just not the growth
team's work. But I think it's a lesson
you learn as kind of like a young
product manager that you can in theory
do lots of ideas, but when you're
responsible for moving metrics, you need
some concept of like the headroom your
projects have. You can't always 100%
forecast it accurately. You're on a team
with six to eight engineers and a
designer and a product manager. like
your two week sprints probably cost
somewhere in the area of $40 to $50,000.
So, you kind of always have to keep like
a mental math back to what's the likely
output of the things we're doing on and
like your company literally will not be
profitable ever if the output of your
sprints doesn't exceed the cost of your
sprints. I think that concept like makes
sense to people. It's a really hard one
to implement in practice. In my
experience, it's not productive to try
to 100% forecast the impact of every
product change you're going to make. But
I think the way I would think about it
is if you were to kind of divide up the
work you're going to do in a quarter
into the buckets of kind of like
technical debt clear down small stuff
and bugs that just kind of has to happen
and big swings. Big swings are typically
where things get expensive where you're
implementing like giant new features or
you're like taking a big shot. I think
those projects definitely need headroom
analysis. You need like a concept of
what the upside could be for all the
money you're going to put into them
through development. You know, a lot of
folks go into these big projects. I'm in
the middle of one right now with my with
my side project weather app. You know,
we've spent the last five months on a
big swing, but honestly, I didn't put
dollar numbers to that. The hardest
thing on the big swings is that you also
don't know how long they're actually
going to take. It's really tough to
estimate those things. Let's start with
the big swings and we'll kind of work
backward from there. When thinking about
those big swings, how do you think about
putting numbers to the potential for a
big swing across my career? It's always
helped me to do the basic math. So,
it's, you know, we have an LTV of like
$100. We think this feature is going to
increase early life cycle usage and
therefore lower churn and therefore
increase LTV. I still think it's good to
chart out the basic assumptions of how
many people do we sign up for a month,
how many people activate, on what screen
do you think people would see this
feature, what percent might click on it
and like of that what percent might
adopt it. So that's pretty simplistic
math. It's not going to show you
necessarily if you're right, but it will
show you if your assumptions are wrong.
That's a great way to think about it,
too, because then you're actually having
to force yourself to look at the
numbers. And we'll get into this later
with some of your turn related math. But
if you're only bringing in 100 people a
day or 500 people a day, you do have to
understand that there is a certain
amount of headroom that any one feature
can get adopted. And then part of that
equation, I would imagine, is also will
this lead to greater conversion? Do we
have a hypothesis that this feature will
actually cause more people to convert?
And then will this feature cause more
people to retain? How do you think about
all those factors as well? I guess I
think mostly about where you want to
initially focus. So I think like a
mistake I see in a lot of companies and
I definitely made a ton of times earlier
in my career is like when you are in a
company or if you were a founder working
on stuff, you feel really productive
kicking a lot of stuff off in parallel
because if you have a project tracker,
it gets a ton of lines that show a bunch
of stuff in progress and the team feels
really busy. But the easiest thing to
lose sight of when you're working on a
product is like projects in progress
don't do anything for your business.
They only start to do something for your
business when they go out the door. So
if you have big projects, kind of like
chunking them up into milestones so you
ship things incrementally and start to
slowly test assumptions goes a long way.
I've never been at a company where the
first milestone going out is something
people feel comfortable with. it's
almost always like hackier than you want
it to be or it's not the full
experience. And I think where that can
go wrong is I think when I'm going back
to my point on focus, I think you should
pick points in the your life cycle or
monetization or product to try to
deliberately increase the effectiveness
of and then you stay focused there long
enough to take a couple shots to see if
you can actually improve it. across most
of my career like the biggest wins we
found were always like the third or
fourth swing at something because you
ship something you realize it doesn't
work and if you move on immediately then
unless you were completely off base it
doesn't work ideally you have enough
tracking setup where you can like see
signs of life somewhere or you're
running an AB test and it like the
variant didn't get totally crushed by
the control that you realize you're like
kind of on to something because I think
when you move on too quickly it's like
it takes teach your engineers a little
bit of time to learn that area of the
codebase. So there's certain like
knowledge debt that they pay down to
figure out how to work there. Same with
the designers, same of the founders,
etc. How do you think about some of
these big swings impacting top of
funnel? For example, my side project,
weather app, the big thing we've been
stuck on is a feature that my hypothesis
is that one, I'll be able to get some
press around it because it's very
innovative. two, it's a kind of feature
that I think will do really well in
marketing. So, I think this is a thing
we can finally, you know, spin up some
Tik Tok videos, advertise it on Meta.
It's a kind of feature that I think will
get people's attention. Now, did I do
anything to validate those assumptions?
No. And this is where it's easy to get
stuck, but how do you think about top
ofunnel in relation to these big swings?
Yeah, I think you can take big swings
anywhere. I think the thing at least
I've always tried to optimize for is
like cost of learning something versus
payoff. If you think something could go
viral or get picked up or be splashy,
it's like how hacky are you comfortable
being building something that can
validate that without fully releasing it
across lots of different types of
entrepreneurship. Like can you pre-ell
access to something is a classic way of
validating an early stage assumption or
could you just use mock-ups and test
that on Tik Tok and not get like stuck
behind the whole development cost.
Everybody has a little bit of a
different comfort level in terms of like
how growth hacky you want to be to
validate something. If you go too far,
the product feels spammy. The product
feels wildly disconnected from the
actual experience. Everybody's seen
mobile gaming ads where the actual game
looks nothing like the advertisements.
So, I think there's definitely like a
balance to strike there. The funniest
thing in mobile gaming though is that
once people saw all those fake ads
getting so much attention, they went and
started building the games that were
actually the experience that the ads
portrayed. And from what I understand,
some of those have done relatively well.
But yeah, I think it's it's a great
concept. I mean, the tricky thing there
is how much do you tip your hand to your
future product? I mean, have you ever
done those kind of hacky validations?
And how do you get comfortable around
not getting ripped off? I mean, I think
that's a big concern for a lot of folks,
myself included, that if I show this
publicly, people will just rip it off
and then beat me to the punch. Um, I I
think that's relatively illogical, but
maybe there is some truth to that. Like,
how do you how do you balance those kind
of illogical fears versus maybe there is
some truth to that? across the companies
that I've worked for or consulted with,
the ones that do the best are the ones
that are the fastest and like know the
direction they want to move in. So to
me, it's like that is the most important
thing. So companies that like I've seen
struggle more like they spread
themselves too thin too early or they
take too long trying to build something
and validate the concept. When I was at
Code Academy, we were the leader in that
little industry of learning to code at
the time, which was big at the time. We
saw companies copy stuff that we were
doing that I knew didn't work and we
just like never cleaned it up because we
moved on to something else. But like
there's a ton of other learn to code
tools that duplicated features we built
that like we saw didn't work or we saw
be neutral or like ineffective and they
copied it assuming that we knew what we
were doing. But in reality like we were
also testing something that we saw not
work and then we just like left it live
because we got distracted and we moved
on to other stuff. That's hilarious. So
then the answer there is maybe you do
that validation at the point at which
you know you can deliver on it rapidly
enough to not worry about that
competition. And then that's really just
a fundamental skill of a business
especially these days with AI assisted
development and other stuff. the pace of
development is just moving so quickly
and the pace of being able to copy
something is moving so quickly so you
just need to be ahead of that as a
business or you're not gonna stick
around. Yeah, definitely. I think like
the point on what to copy is like to me
like a nuanced one. It's like I think
you the founder or the product team or
whoever you are, you should be
opinionated on like the types of
features you should build and you should
not look to competitors unless you're
like woefully under the baseline on what
you should build next. I think once
you're building a feature, you should
look at the best practices and reinvent
as little of the wheel as possible. So
if you're building like a document
finder, like look at Google Docs, look
at SharePoint, look at Finder in Mac,
look at all the little features those
things have and those are probably the
baseline. Whether you should have a
document finder is kind of up to you.
But it's like once you're committed to a
feature set, just steal all the best
practices from the people who are the
best at it. Might not be your
competitors. Might be people who do that
as the core business. Yeah, it's a
really good point too that you never
know what is actually working and what's
not working when you look at things from
the outside. I see this a ton in the app
industry of people tweeting, "Oh, this
app is making 200k a month. Copy these
five steps." And then for some of those
actually know the folks who build the
app and I know, you know, four of the
five points that this growth hacker made
on Twitter, it's like that's not why the
business is being successful. Those four
things are completely irrelevant and
aren't what's fundamentally driving the
business. It's this other thing that you
just can't even see. Even though you can
look now across Tik Tok and Meta and
other platforms to see which ads are
being shown a ton, you don't always even
know whether those ads that are shown a
ton are actually profitable or not. And
then even if they are actually
profitable for that app, would it then
actually be profitable for your app? I
think people lean a little too much on
this on copying the wrong things without
really understanding the deeper context
behind them. Exactly. I feel like that's
why I kind of write my blog in the style
that I do. I get the appeal of looking
at other companies and like there are
tools now where you can observe their AB
tests and it's like see they shipped one
thing and then another thing and they
went with the other thing and it's like
it's unclear from the outside if that's
true. like if they calculated that
correctly, if they went with something
that wasn't actually the winner. So
also, it's really unclear if that would
apply to you, the company. So to me,
it's more important to like look at the
theory behind why these things work and
care less about the exact
implementations. We've uh chased a few
rabbits here, but I did want to circle
back to the other couple of things you
talked about in this kind of ROI
equation. One of them is the small
things. And how do you think about
paying back the technical debt, making
small changes, and the ROI of of these
smaller things along the way versus the
big swings, which we've talked about?
Yeah, think about it kind of like an
investment portfolio where you need a
certain percentage in each bucket. So,
if you're just starting out, you
probably don't have a lot of technical
debt. There's probably still like a
layer of technical cleanup that has to
happen or shuttering old features or
updating libraries and scripts, etc.
Maybe you only need like 10% of your
quarterly development time going to
that, but you need some percent. Or the
product starts to get stale and
technically really hard to manage. If
you were at a giant company like
Microsoft, they could be paying off 50%
of their roadmap with technical debt
items. I think it depends a lot on the
the phase of life. I think in the kind
of like smaller optimizations bucket, I
think it's really easy for teams to get
lost pursuing just the bigger things and
forgetting about basic product quality,
especially in certain areas like
purchase flows, onboarding. There's
certain parts of the application where
100% of your users go through it and
they go through it at times where
they're not really sure if they're
staying with your product. To me, those
things should be polished to a mirror
finish. So, it's a thing I've talked
about a couple places, but one of the
highest ROI projects we ever did at Code
Academy is we rewrote all of the check
out PGR copy. So, like if you plugged in
a payment and it didn't work, making
sure you got a message back that
actually told you what to do and didn't
just say like invalid payment method,
please contact your bank. Tell them
what's wrong. Tell them what to fix it.
If it doesn't work, send them PayPal.
PayPal doesn't work, send them back to a
card. It literally took like two days of
downloading stuff, stack ranking the
errors, rewriting it, remerging it back
to the codebase and like maybe that
let's say very conservatively lifted
check on page conversion like 1%. But
100% of your new revenue goes through
the checkout page. So it's really like
you lift the whole business's revenue
1%. So for a subscription app that would
be then making sure your onboarding
through payw wall are just incredibly
dialed in. How do you think about
forming a hypothesis around which things
need work? I would imagine
tracking each page in the onboarding,
getting good analytics around where
people are dropping off, why they're
dropping off, and kind of finding the
rough edges because I mean this is again
something I personally struggle with,
something I see so many people
struggling with is that you're trying to
build this perfect product, but you're
perfecting areas that don't matter. So,
how do you find the places that actually
matter so that this 25 to 50% of your
bug fixes and technical debt and smaller
projects are still impactful projects
versus just polishing something that
doesn't matter. I think it's always a
mix of art and science. So, I think I
always want the highest level of
analytic setup I can get to. I think
it's tempting to just view funnels,
especially early stage funnels, is you
look at the place with the biggest drop
off and you like start to intuitively
work there. But inherently like some of
the parts of the funnel will have a big
drop off. I prefer to work bottom up. So
go from like the highest intent people
back up. It's really hard to convince
people of stuff. So you should start
with the people who are already
convinced. In purchase flows, it's
always the people who try to click
payment and it doesn't work for some
reason. That's like under your control.
So, if you're selling through an app
store, this matters less. But if you're
selling on a web checkout page, this
matters a lot more. And go through areas
of like bugs, confusion, dead end. I
think a really good surveying technique
is right after purchase. You get kind of
like one shot at asking an open-ended
question of like, was there anything
about the purchase experience that
didn't work for you? Was it confusing?
Or like, is there any questions you had
about this product before purchase that
you couldn't find an answer to? And it's
like you'll never get a flood of
information through that, but you'll get
like two, three, four, five things a
week that start to like build your
intuition around like what could be
wrong in the funnel. Like another thing
that helps a ton is just like have
people who've never seen it before go
through it with fresh eyes. So these
could be your friends, these can be user
testing.com people. Like you, the person
building this, have stared at this thing
for so long. But frequently when I
consult with clients, it's like I can
see really obvious things because I've
never seen these flows before. But the
person who built it like knows this is
version three and like this part looks
weird because this was done between
version two and version three. There was
like a really good reason for that at
the time. But to a fresh customer, they
don't know. If you're five people and
everybody's kind of focused and working
together, that looks really different.
But if you're a 50 or 100 person
company, I saw a tweet I think just this
morning saying if you're the CEO of a
SAS company, you should on board with
your product at least quarterly because
teams underneath you are changing things
rapidly enough that you don't know
what's going on. So maybe even part of
your practice as a larger company should
be having the CEO having another team go
through the onboarding looking for that
in addition to people with zero context
outside of the company looking at that
on a regular basis. Yeah. Exactly. I
think a classic place to look for things
to fix is the lines between teams. So
like if one team runs the ad and the
other team manages the landing pages,
there's no guarantee there's any
continuity between the ads and the
landing pages. It's like a classic place
you find lowhanging fruit. If like team
A owns this step, team B owns this step,
team C owns this step. No one's paying
attention to the user gap to the gaps
and experience between those things
because each team gets kind of like
focused on their area totally naturally.
Yeah. and and the app stores, it's
really easy for those kind of things to
happen as well if your screenshots
weren't changed for the last 6 months.
And don't even mention the feature that
you now know is like one of your higher
converting features. You know, that
needs to be maybe screenshot one or two
in your app store page if you've built
this new feature and think that that's
what's driving a lot of your
conversions. But it's easy to lose sight
of that fullfunnel experience. U or like
you said at bigger apps it's maybe that
the ASO team is working so independently
from the monetization team that they
don't even realize that this new feature
or some change or or some AB test that
one is driving a ton that they could
pull up into the screenshots and other
marketing copy and things like that.
Yeah, exactly. And I think when you're a
product person or designer and engineer
working on one feature set, whenever you
do customer interviews, you want to ask
them about that feature set. But to the
user, it's all just one experience.
Everything from your email marketing to
your ads to your app store page to the
product itself to the things they hear
about you is just kind of like one blob
of opinion. So to them, it's like it's
all one experience. Even though like I'm
really curious about how when I was at
Uber, like how did they like the ranking
of the homepage? But like they don't
think like that. They think of could I
find food? Did it show up on time? And
was it good? Even that journey is across
like thousands and thousands of people
work on all that stuff together. Yeah,
it's crazy. The next thing I want to
talk about is you most recently wrote a
post about this idea of having a growth
ceiling. And that's the fact that, you
know, depending on the number of people
you have coming in and your turn rate,
you can actually calculate how far you
can grow based on that. and tell me
about this concept and then we'll go
through how that works in practice.
Yeah, definitely. There's a couple like
really good rules of thumb to know
within subscription products. Probably
the handiest is like one divided by your
monthly churn rate as a decimal point is
your average months of retention. So if
you have like a 20% month overmonth
churn, that's 0.2. One divided by 0.2 is
five. So your average user will be
around for five months. So you obviously
see the power in that equation of
reducing churn like dramatically
increases the length of retention have
another implication of that is every
time you cut churn in half you double
that number. So like if you divide one
by 0.1 you get 10. So just it's not easy
to reduce churn that much but reducing
churn is super super powerful. An
equation that we didn't even understand
at Code Academy at the time is if you
take the number of users that you're
acquiring per month and divide that by
your month-to-month churn rate, you get
the ceiling of users that you can keep
at that level. So if you have 500 users
coming in per month and you're churning
10% of them per month like 500 divided
by 0.1 is 5,000. So at 5,000 the number
in which the inputs will equal the
outputs. So unless you drop churn or you
pick up the acquisition, your growth
ceiling basically is you'll never be
able to grow above 5,000 users. So this
is something that I commonly see in
subscription products. When before
you're at that threshold, your user base
numbers will just keep increasing. And
it's tempting to think that your product
work is going really, really well. But
what we should really keep an eye on is
churn, the numbers that are upstream of
churn and your acquisition numbers.
Because if your growth ceiling is 5,000
people and you're at 3,000 people,
you're just going to kind of drift up
from a subscriber-based number,
regardless of your actions, assuming
churn and acquisition don't change. So,
it's easy to assume it's going really,
really well, but you have to be very
precise with what you're tracking. Yeah,
I see this all the time and we we've
talked about on the podcast before.
There does seem to be a ceiling for a
lot of subscription apps in the million
to 10 million range, sometimes 10 to 20
million range where you kind of hit
that. And it's kind of cool that you're
mathematically describing the ceiling.
But it does seem to be that without some
new growth lever, without some big
improvement in churn, you just start
churning out the same number of users
you're bringing in and you just kind of
hit the ceiling. So, you're growing,
growing, growing, and it's looking good
and you're drifting up. Maybe even
you're not drifting up, but you're
growing really rapidly, but then you
just kind of hit this this ceiling and
equating it to turn and being able to
calculate, I think, is really powerful.
We'll put a link to this blog post in
the show notes. But how do you think
about that for annual because it's not
quite as easy to do the math on that?
Yeah, I mean, the month-over-month churn
rate is really like a blended average of
all of your churn across monthly and
annual plans. I think the way I think
about that for I guess in most
subscription businesses is you should
look at this cohorted. So for every like
month of users that sign up, what is
their like month 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 etc. like
churn rate and you should look at that
across both of your plan types. I think
the best way of getting ahead of churn
is not basing retention off of payments.
It's basing off of some sort of core
action in the product. So, if you're
Slack, for example, and someone signs up
for a monthly plan, they might send zero
messages for three months and just
forget you're charging them 1999, but
they're probably churning eventually.
So, if you really want to average
retention in a product, figure out what
the core action is. So, in your weather
app, it should be I expect you to come
in and check the weather three times a
week or four times a week or one time a
week or something like that because that
will always like improving core
activation and the core habit will
always improve churn. Once someone is in
the mental space of turnurning, there
are things you can do, but it's hard.
There's a couple mitigating steps you
can take, but it's not nearly as
effective as fixing it upstream. I want
to dive a little bit more into term
mitigation, and you've written a lot
about that. I think that's kind of one
of the focuses of your blog is churn and
retention. But before we dive into that,
I did want to ask h how do you factor in
the kind of long tale? Because I've
talked to enough apps in my role here.
I've done office hours for years and
then you having my own apps and then the
thing is most apps retention doesn't go
to zero. It goes to
some percentage of that initial cohort.
So if you're looking at let's say year
one you acquire 10,000 subscribers and
you know 60% of those turn. So you have
4,000 subscribers but then by by year
two you're not turnurning another 60% of
subscribers. You're maybe only turning
30% of those subscribers. And so like
looking at my own app, I still have 10%
of monthly subscribers and I think maybe
even a little higher of annual
subscribers from 8 years ago. But that
you know 10% 8% you know that that's not
a really fat tail. A lot of the the apps
that I've talked to that are doing
really well and building a fantastic
business that line flat lines more like
20%, 25% where you know you churn a
higher rate the first year, a lower rate
the second year and by the third or
fourth year you kind of have Eric
Crowley has this idea of tourists versus
locals of tourists like you're going to
have people who come and check out your
app and it's not a good fit or it's a
good fit for a short amount of time but
then they move on and then you have the
locals being the people who your
solution becomes part of their daily,
monthly, weekly life, and they're just
going to stick around for for years,
maybe decades. So, how do you factor in
that long-term retention in this
equation of what your growth ceiling is?
I take the month overmonth average,
factoring all the plans to calculate
your uh just month- over-month turn
rate. Again, month-to-month churn rate
is not as helpful as knowing the
cohorted and plan-based churn levels.
But I think if you have a retention
curve that like flattens at some point,
it's really good. You always want it to
flatten higher. Um, but if you don't
have it flatten ever, if those curves go
to zero, it's really, really hard to
grow your user base and you're going to
have a higher monthly churn. So, you
can't stack a big user base if 100% of
your people after month seven go to zero
because you'll have to acquire so many
people to get that. And you always have
a bucket that takes a little while, but
100% of the things you pour into it
leaks out. I mean, all subscription
products are leaky buckets, but you want
that leak as small as possible. I think
when I think about why that happens, to
me, the least discussed part of churn
management is the underlying use case
you solve for. So like your retention
length will be really dictated by how
long the user has the problem you're
solving for and like how much they need
your solution to do it. So, if you think
of like cell phone plans, like I don't
know how long I've been on Google Fi,
but probably like eight years, nine
years. Like, if they don't screw
anything up, I'll probably be with them
25 years because like I have a daily
need for their product and the
workarounds and backups to them, like
none of them are compelling to me. And I
realistically need a cell phone. So, my
guess is that cell phone retention plans
year-over-year retain 80% of people,
like 90% of people, like maybe minus
some switching, maybe I'm off, but you'd
have really, really high retention.
Contrast that with like meditation apps
where like meditation is like a thing
you don't really need an app for. You'll
probably either like learn it and like
it or realize it's not for you like
relatively quickly. So the only way you
can scale like Headspace or Comm is you
need millions of people or you need a
plan structure that like locks them in.
I think we're seeing that a lot with AI
apps right now is that Studio Gibli
converting your avatar and pictures and
stuff. OpenAI just blew up with that
which I don't think they even expected
but Sam Alman's been tweeting about
their servers melting and adding a
million users in an hour. That may be
the fastest product growth. You know
there were starting from a massive base.
I mean, the chat GPT app is already
massive and they already have a massive
subscriber base and then to be adding a
million users in an hour was just
insane. So, they had this viral moment,
but to your point, if that's the primary
use case, people are going to turn out
because they're not going to be
converting their photos on a weekly,
daily basis, and you need other use
cases for that to be a sustaining
subscription for OpenAI. I mean, you
would hope that people get in and start
seeing the utility and using it for a
multitude of things, but I think there's
a lot of AI apps that blow up and then
there's not that kind of sustaining use
case. Yeah, I think you kind of hit on
the nail on the head of like if you
don't have a sustaining use case, one,
it might not be a good fit for a
subscription product or it might be not
a good fit for a subscription product
for most people. So you can see kind of
like AI headshot generation being great
for like PR people or photographers or
like heads of HR as a company who want
everyone in their company to have the
same headshot format or whatever. So
there might be like a subset of personas
where those things work for. But if you
don't tackle like a long-term recurring
use case and provide value at like a
cadence that exceeds what someone is
wants and therefore they're willing to
pay for it, it's really really tough to
build a subscription product. I think if
you were to like bucket the types of
subscriptions that people pay for, you
have the really long-term stuff like
mortgages, financing products, loans,
rent, cell phones, healthcare, where
like those problems never go away
effectively and you can build giant
monopolies in those spaces. You then
have the short to medium-term use cases
of like dating, fitness, dieting,
language learning, gaming where like
those are things people stick with for a
couple months. a subset of them will
stick with them for a long time, but
really that's because they like your
product a lot and they don't switch, but
the underlying like need fades away.
Although, you know, in gaming, it has
been interesting to see, you know,
Fortnite and some of these other
companies, the way they've created this
kind of sustaining use case is that
entertainment is a long-term use case,
but people get bored and then go try
other MMOs or other ways to get that
entertainment. And the way some of these
big game companies have been solving for
that is with season passes and things
like that where the product itself is
changing enough to bring people back in
on a regular basis with these new
characters, new game modes, new
collaborations with big IP and things
like that. So even if your use case is
shortterm, you know, perfect example
with chat GBT is like, okay, a bunch of
people came in to convert their photo
because it looked really cute, but then
there are a ton of other use cases for
chat GBT. And so then, you know, as
they're able to expose users to those
other use cases and get them deeper into
the product, there are those sustaining
use cases that will be used on a more
regular basis. And those are the kind of
things that that even if you kind of
start out of the gate with a explosive
viral success, like this is what you
should be looking for is that next
season of Fortnite kind of thing where
you keep building the use case or
keeping it fresh enough to keep people
coming back. Definitely. I think the
recipe that works in the shorter term
use cases is you need massive audience
size. like a surefire recipe to die as a
subscription company is short life cycle
small audience where it's like you just
won't be able to acquire enough people
and this thing will never grow. I think
kind of what you hit on with the
Fortnite season pass is what I would
call like a companion subscription
product. So like Uber Eatats has one
Uber has one of these Door Dash has one
of these Lyft has one of these where
you're in a long-term use case but
there's like a high ability to switch
between providers. So they end up
building these kind of like pass
products really as a retention tool. So
like if I'm paying Uber Eats, I forget
what their membership product is, but
they'll call it like $9.99 a month in
the US. I'm way less likely to use Door
Dash. And because Uber makes its money
through the core business, you have a
lot of flexibility in terms of how you
price the subscription product, but
really what it does is stop you from
switching. I imagine like Fortnite
thinks of it the same. Yeah, totally. In
that blog post on churn, you go through
five kind of key areas of what drives
churn. And so you you already covered
that first one of how long will users
have the problem you solve? But the next
one is how strong is your product market
fit? Yeah, it's a great question. I
think like you said, the first thing
that will dictate overall retention is
how long do people want to be solving
the problem that you ultimately solve.
The second one is like how good are you
at solving that problem, which I would
call product market fit. To me, there's
there's two kind of ways of measuring
product market fit. There's the classic
kind of Shan Ellis hacking growth survey
where you survey a bunch of users and
you ask what percentage couldn't live
without the product and you want 40% or
higher, the people that couldn't live
without the product. I think that's
really good for earlier stage companies
when it's tough to know your retention
numbers and you can survey people
relatively quickly, get data back
relatively quickly. I think the better
way of measuring retention is like
trying to chart out the percentage of a
cohort that keeps doing the same action
like month over month. So for your app
it'd be like what percent come back and
check the weather x times per week. And
if you graph that like you're saying you
probably see it flatten which means like
for whatever segment of that user base
that is like you have product market
fit. So the other thing that I keep in
mind is there's degrees of product
market fit. So there's kind of like this
works for me and I like it but if given
a better alternative I'll switch or
there's this thing is the best thing
I've ever used for this. And I think the
way of looking at that is if you can as
best you can segment by persona or some
concept of persona you should ideally
see like good retention for one of them
which means you're kind of on to
something. Yeah. And using my weather
app as an example it kind of hits your
earlier point about use case duration.
And one of the reasons, even though it's
a ridiculously competitive space, even
though it's really hard, one of the
reasons I keep at it is that weather is
one of those indefinite continual use
cases where people will check the
weather for probably the rest of their
life. And then for me thinking through
this as you were saying that you know
the fact that my long-term retention is
in those like low high single digits
maybe low double digits of 8 to 10 to
12%. That's probably a good sign for me
of product market fit that I have some
level of product market fit but not
great product market fit. If I had great
product market fit because the use case
is indefinite, I with great product
market fit should be landing closer to
20% maybe even higher than 20% in that
kind of long-term retention. And that's
maybe a thing to look at for me to watch
over time and for people listening to go
look at your long-term cohort retention.
We actually in the revenue cat
dashboard. This is where I always look
at it, of course, but we have that
cohorted retention where you can see
across all time, you know, what's that
retention curve look like? And then you
can go and cohort it and look at
different years, different date
durations and look at is that improving
over time or is that getting worse over
time, you know, did a new feature change
that in any meaningful ways? But yeah, I
I hadn't thought of that until you said
that that that long-term cohort is a
very direct sign of the level of product
market fit that you have. And if you're
an early exchange company, like you
might be at a long-term use case and it
might take 14 months to like see those
curves flatten. And if you're only at
month six of building an app, like
that's tough. But I think if you look at
each cohort coming in, you should see
the early stage months like stack up to
be slightly higher. That will depend on
like where you get users from. Like it's
a very common thing that companies will
go viral and you'll see a flood of
people come in but they're not really
your persona and like that cohort
retains terribly. So even though it's
like good for the metrics overall, the
question is always like of the people
you're either paying to acquire,
building SEO content for acquire, using
word of mouth funnels to acquire, are
they the right type of person? You
always care about the long-term LTB of
the monthly cohorts that you retain.
This goes back to our earlier discussion
as well about not knowing what is and
isn't successful for other companies.
So, when you see an app go like insanely
viral and you're super jealous because
you're still, you know, just running
meta ads to get people into the app or
whatever, you're like, "Ah, if my app
could only go viral, half the time, and
probably more than half the time, really
isn't a great way to acquire users
unless you have those other things
stacked up, and we're going to keep
going through them, but you don't get to
see those numbers. You only get to see
the Tik Tok that does, you know, 10
million views. you don't get to see how
many of those actually convert into
paying users, how many of those paying
users stay subscribed and like was that
actually a good cohort and the answer is
often it isn't. So another thing where
you can look at the numbers but like
completely misunderstand what's actually
going on behind the scenes. Yeah, you
care about stacking up a user base that
will like pay you for a long time and
pay you well as best you can. You should
be guiding product development and
growth of the earliest stage indicators
of that. So like onboarding success,
activation success, certain personas,
like segmenting audiences and then
feeding that back into whatever
acquisition machine you have. So if you
acquire a thousand users a month, but
15% of them are, let's say, coffee
baristas and coffee baristas want to
know the weather for XYZ reason, and
they're the best fit. There's nothing
wrong with other types of people coming
towards the application, but if you're
going to spend money and time, you
should focus on where you're going to
hit the longest term payoff. Totally.
And that actually brings us to the next
point in your blog post is that how well
you activate users is a huge part of
retention. So I say after you have like
a level of product market fit. The big
question in activation is like how many
people experience the value of the
product early on. So it's like the
classic milestones within product
development to track this are kind of
like sign up, how many people register,
set up, how many people like take the
steps necessary to receive value from
the product. So that could be setting up
your profile or turning on location
services so you can see the weather or
something like that. Then there's kind
of like the first aha moments of what
percentage of people see value. So, like
I was going to go on a hike and your app
told me it was going to rain and I
didn't go on a hike or I thought it was
going to be cloudy today and you
notified me of weather change and that's
like a great early happy experience for
users. And then first 30 days activation
and then long-term retention as best you
can especially the early stages you want
to make sure people are experiencing
like the win on the application as fast
as possible. I think if you look at any
classic benchmark reports especially
around trials like people make trial
whether I will or will not start a trial
experience like almost in session zero
probably within the first like 10
minutes on the application maybe
quicker. So it's like being really clear
on what you do and guiding people to do
that in the first session is really
really helpful. There's things you can
do around like life cycle marketing that
they don't in the first session. There's
ways of guiding them back. But going
back to headroom analysis, really good
email campaigns have like a 30% open
rate and like a net 2% clickthrough
rate. So it's like once you lose them on
a product, it's tough. The next one is
payment processing. And for subscription
apps, you know, more heavily reliant on
the app stores. Maybe that's less of an
issue, but that does kind of encapsulate
that entire conversion event of like how
many people are you actually getting to
convert. How do you think about that?
Yeah, definitely less of a problem for
app storebased apps. So even though the
30% fee that Apple and Android put on
applications, you do get a lot out of
the box for that. You get a high
converting checkout page, it handles
currencies for you, it's really good at
payment processing, it's really good at
payment retries. You do do a lot of
stuff. If you build off the web, this is
more your problem. So the number one
thing I'm always looking at or the two
things in payment processing rates is
after someone clicks pay on your
checkout page, what percentage of time
do you collect the money? So like almost
no one tracks this the first time, but
it's the highest intent people you can
possibly get. A certain amount of those
fails will be valid. Like they their
card won't have a balance, but there's a
surprising amount that if you look into
the details, you can try to find ways of
optimizing for. A classic one is like
US-based companies who charge around the
world and they still only use Stripe or
US-based gateways. So there's regions
like India where like the US-based
payment system is not as effective. Same
with China. The bigger you are, the more
kind of like headroom there is in like
starting to set up secondary payment
providers or getting a subscription
manager. For app based stuff and for
smaller companies, this doesn't apply as
much at all. But I think the philosophy
of it takes so much effort to get
someone to try to click pay lose as many
as few of those people as possible. The
second one is recurring payment success
rate. So the classic things to do here
is the classic dunning and email
notifications when payments fail. I
think again the app store handles most
of this stuff for you. I think in the
app store you still might be able to
detect this and customize some emails to
get people to update their payment
method. I've always seen, again, it's
not a massive uplift, but there's value
in spending like two days copywriting
those emails because this is going to
impact a 100% of your people who fail
payments. And the lower your churn rate
gets, the more likely most of your churn
is payment based churn. So, like if you
get turn rate all the way down to 2%,
50% might be payment based churn. And
for apps, you know, a lot of apps are
getting really good at when people click
your CTA. And this is always kind of a
tricky thing with the app stores and
honestly any CTA is that you can get
more people to click a button that's
more obtuse. When it's just start free
trial and the actual price is hidden
somewhere in the fine print. You can
juice the number of people who are going
to click your CTA. But then when the app
store sheet pops up and tells you the
actual terms and the actual price, you
know how many people are clicking your
CTA and then dismissing the payment
sheet and not completing that. And
that's probably a multiffactorial thing
of the less clear you made the pricing
on your payw wall, probably the higher
rate of people who are going to go ahead
and cancel the actual payment because
they didn't know what they were signing
up for. And then it's always kind of a
balance of like how do you balance how
many people are clicking on it versus
how many people are actually starting
the free trial. I've actually been
experimenting in my app and I haven't
seen many people do this. But when
people click the CTA and then cancel the
payment, I actually pop a little modal
now that gives them a non-recurring free
trials, a reverse free trial. So I offer
a reverse free trial to customers where
they get 7 days completely free that
doesn't renew. And I haven't seen a ton
of success with that. So I'm not going
to say this is like a magic bullet. But
I think those kind of experiments are
what you're talking about is that when
somebody clicks your CTA that is high
signal. Again, maybe lower signal if
your CTA is confusing or or not clear on
the price and things like that. But it's
something you want to be experimenting
with and and that's a really great place
to experiment. A lot of apps now when
you dismiss the payment sheet they'll
offer a discount immediately and kind of
try and win you back that way
immediately and that can be incredibly
effective. I mean a lot of apps are
doing that now. Although I have heard
Apple has been hassling some developers
about that that it's kind of a form of
price
discrimination which is understandable
if you're just randomly giving people
50% off because they dismiss a payment
sheet. you know, that's maybe not the
best customer experience, but it can be
incredibly effective. And so, this kind
of goes to what you're saying is that
that payment section, whether on the web
or in the app, is a place to spend a lot
of time and be thinking a lot about. The
last one on your list is how good are
you at winning people back once they
leave? So, you kind of already touched
on it that this is actually really hard
and maybe that's why it's at the bottom
of your list, but what are some of the
strategies you've seen be successful
here? And then realistically, what do
you think people can expect? And then
kind of back to the whole ROI
discussion, maybe the the ROI on this is
so low that especially for an earlier
stage app when the numbers are just low,
it's just not a place to invest a lot
into. So I think if you look at really
big subscription companies like the New
York Times is one, like Clear is another
one, the US travelbased app in their
cancellations flows, they're always
taking every shot they can to try to win
you back regardless of what you click on
the survey. So, if you click like, it's
too expensive, they'll give you a
temporary two-month discount. Zoom does
this, too. If you click on like, you
know, I had a negative experience,
they'll connect you with customer
support. If you click on like, you know,
I'm too busy right now, they'll let you
pause the subscription. I'd say this
tactic set is not the cheapest to
implement because typically it involves
like bespoke logic in your payment
processor. So, if you're web- based and
you use Stripe, I don't think Stripe has
any outofthe-box features that help you
here. So, you have to custom manage all
this logic. But there's a reason all the
giant companies do it. I've implemented
this a couple times across a couple
companies. I'd say the big three that
I've seen work is pause like discount
and kind of like connect with support.
Pause works the best if it's a temporary
habit. So we implemented this code
academy like people don't want to learn
to code every day of the week unlimited.
They go through like periods of
learning. So if you let them pause and
let them come back when they're less
busy, they're more likely to retain in
the long term. Like if my mortgage
offered pause, I don't think anyone
would use it because either like you
need your mortgage or you don't. Like
the underlying need doesn't really go
away. Same with discounts. I'd say the
two discount s strategies that I see
work is like temporary discount. So
we'll keep you in the same plan
structure for 3 months at a 50% off and
then we'll auto readjust you back or
like we'll drop you down to a lower like
hidden tier of the product. So, when you
go to at least when I went to cancel
Zoom, I think I was paying 15 bucks a
month for Zoom and they offered me like
a $7 a month plan, but it's only five
calls. The calls came longer than 40
minutes or something like that. So, it's
instead of losing you completely, they
let you shift down. I think the risk
here is that you should keep an eye on
the percentage of your users that go for
those discounts. Like most what I would
call like growth tactics, they get
widely known. So years and years ago, it
became known in the internet that if you
went and added a bunch of stuff to a
checkout cart and then didn't purchase
out, most of those companies would then
just email you a coupon code to bring
you back. And that like works until most
of people know to do that behavior and
just everybody recoups the discount. I
think this tactic set is going to go in
the same direction. That said, when I've
implemented this, I've seen between like
a 10 and 20% drop in churn. Depends a
little bit on the use case, but like it
adds up to be material. There's a reason
all the giant companies do this. It's
not the world's cheapest tactic set to
implement, but like definitely, you
know, rounds the sharp edges off your
churn numbers. The complexity piece is a
tough one. I mean, you know, we don't
talk about revenue a ton on the podcast,
but this is something we're trying to
solve right now specifically with our
customer center product where you can
actually drop a button into your
settings or wherever you want to put it
of like manage subscription or whatever
and then when people go to cancel, you
can initiate a survey. Okay. And so by
building out this tooling, we are trying
to remove some of that complexity.
That's maybe a point for look for the
easy wins in those flows and look for
tooling and other things that can help
you get those easy wins versus spinning
up a whole project where you're spending
months on this where maybe there is like
as we discussed at the earlier in the
podcast where there's so much other
lowhanging fruit that you should be
focusing on that this is maybe not where
you should you know do a three-month
massive project to build out this really
big custom internal tool until you're
further along where the number of people
you get back will be enough of a
meaningful impact to justify that three
months of building and whatnot. Yeah,
definitely. I think the I don't know
it's another lesson from 10 plus years
in product now is like the complexity
tax is real. It's like the northstar of
your development should be protecting
like future velocity. So it's like you
can do things now that make things
incrementally more effective but you
have to manage this codebase forever. So
a classic tactic that every subscription
company eventually does is geobbased
pricing. So you realize like the Nordic
countries have the highest willingness
to pay along with like Western Europe
and the US and Canada. And you know
there's a second tier of companies that
can pay less and then there's like a
third tier of companies that will pay
the least. And you start to like
localize price level in addition to
currency and like what appears on the
page. That tactic almost always works in
making your total user base produce more
cash, but also you have to then manage
10 P price packages forever. So every
time you list pricing in your ads or in
email or in your customer support docs,
you now have to manage this complexity
forever. So it's like it's effective,
but you should squeeze, in my opinion,
the easier tactics out first. But like
we did at Code Academy, it's effective,
but like you you kind of can't unring
that bell. And now when you do price
changes, you have 10 price tiers to
think about and like currencies change
in fluctuation to each other. So it's
you're probably pegging the FX rates
initially, but then like how do you
manage the change? It's just another
thing you have to pay attention to.
Yeah, there's so many things, you know,
as an indie, I mean, I've been very
fortunate just working on the app stores
of so much of this complexity is
abstracted away by the app stores, but I
haven't I haven't done regional pricing
yet. And and part of it is exactly what
you're saying and this is where it's
tough to manage that complexity over
time. Even price testing on the app
stores, you end up with a bunch of
different SKs and you can different end
up with different subscription groups
and it can just become a huge mess and
you got to factor that into the the ROI
calculations. Yeah. How much complexity
does this add to the business long term?
Even pricing tiers, you know, we've
talked about it a lot on the podcast.
You know, it's great to introduce a new
pricing tier, but that's a lot of
complexity that now you have to support
forever. The multiple tiers, what
features get unlocked, what features
don't. But it's worth doing. It's just
figuring out the right time to do it in
the stage of your business and
everything. Yeah, exactly. I think Code
Academy introduced a tier above our
normal tier after I'd left, I think. So,
I think we were already like north of 50
million a year before we hit a second
tier. you can build as many pricing
tiers as like you can make great
products, but like the distance between
good and great is way longer than people
think. So, it's like the your
monetization systems as a whole are
really just like a measure of how much
of the value your product produces that
you capture in money. So, it's like
typically the best thing is you make
your product as strong as possible. Then
you figure out how much you want to
monetize. But I think it's really easy
when you start making money to make the
monetization system the goal in itself
and lose track of like the you just
collect a percentage of the value people
feel in your product. And there's
definitely tactics and ways to make that
more effective. But if the product isn't
increasing in value, it's really tough
to raise your prices. Well, I think
that's a a great place to wrap up. It
all does ultimately come back to
product. You have to build something
that's actually delivering value for
folks. And then especially as a
subscription app, you have to create
products that deliver value over time or
people just aren't going to stick
around. Well, anything else you wanted
to share as we wrap up? We will share
links to your blog and we'll share links
to the two specific blog posts that we
referenced today. But yeah, anything
else you wanted to share as we wrap up?
I think that's the main thing like you
know I think in summary like we learned
a ton of hard lessons at Code Academy.
It took us five plus years to figure all
these things out that we just talked
about in an hour. I think you know what
I'm trying to do is write as many of
them down as I can on my blog at
subscriptionindex.com. I'm in a place
where I'm like not really scaling the
consulting business because I'm kind of
at capacity. So, I'm literally like
writing down everything that I see to be
effective on the blog. So, hopefully
people going through this journey now
don't have to, you know, take all the
the bumps and bruises that we did
figuring out how to scale your revenue.
Awesome. Well, thanks for sharing some
of those learnings today and it was fun
to get the the more nuanced take. I
mean, you can read, you know, those blog
posts in the past, reread them leading
up to this recording. It's great to get
the kind of behind the scenes. I read
those in like 10 minutes and so, you
know, maybe 15 20 minutes total reading
of the two blog posts, maybe less,
actually. But we talked about it for
over an hour. So, yes, there's just so
much to it. So, thank you for coming on
the podcast and sharing the the more
in-depth from the blog posts. Yeah, of
course. Happy
to. Thanks so much for listening. If you
have a minute, please leave a review in
your favorite podcast player. You can
also stop by
chat.subclub.com to join our private
community.